- All right, as the famous singer Pink said,
let's get this party started.
So, hi everybody, I'm Kevin Kelly.
I'm the Interim Executive Director for the Digital Center
for Innovation Transformation and Equity.
We're one of the co-hosts of this summit
and we're so happy that you all joined us today.
You are in for a treat.
We have an amazing panel of super bright people
and I'm just here to guide the conversation
from planning to practice, robotics and automation
shaping the next generation workforces.
So our cast of characters here
include Mike Appio, Carol Reiley, Roger Tadajewski,
and Richard Chapman.
And I'm gonna ask them to each introduce themselves,
I've given them all license if they wished to have a couple
of slides to talk a little bit about their backgrounds
and the projects they're working on.
And then we'll dive into questions.
So I'm gonna hand it over to Mike.
- Hello, my name is Mike Appio. I'm from DeAnza College.
I'm gonna kind of set the tone here a little bit of
where we came from, where we wanna be
and how this really affects the industrial
automation program that we wanna do.
My aspect's gonna be from we're
at kind of the infancy stage.
Now up here, it's a very established program,
now you're seeing that lab.
So that's what that lab looked like
when I came there in 2008.
We had 10 manual machines and two simulators.
The program has evolved to multi-axis machining,
robotics cells, additive manufacturing
program with six classes.
So over the years, it's really evolved.
So our success back there is what I wanna do.
And once again, we're on the infancy stage of starting one,
but yet we're very well established in the financial stage.
So we'll fill in the blanks.
And now industrial automation technology is gonna be our
strong point in the future of what we're working for.
Now, going back to this really quickly is
we do these programs already.
It'd be advanced manufacturing quality technician
additive manufacturing.
Our expansion recently has been multi-axis CNC machining
and I'll go back that, but our way into automation was
robotic work cells with Fenical arms
and things of that nature, which is a great
segue into the automation.
Our problem was we needed technicians
to fix these robots and run the equipment.
Our program now, and as you'll talk later,
and I definitely wanna get a shout out to Richard,
'cause Richard at Hartnell has been kind
of the base agriculture that we're in the tech area.
But we're gonna start a program
and talk later about some industrial automation systems
with Festo and are aligned in industry recognized
certifications, which they'll cover here with NC3
as a start, which is a great, great start to do that.
I'm gonna move in.
Now as we get going on this,
we have the plan to move it.
We have Festo NC3s to start out our program along things,
just to give you an idea of the innovation
that we've had and how it's financed was
many years through CACT, this is going way back,
DeAnza actually had a full blown
industrial automation program in the late
nineties and two thousands.
But I believe it was so far ahead of its time
that it wasn't successful.
But we do have that background.
We do have other people that found a foundation
that over a million dollars put in the program.
Lemme talk a little about the NSFAT grant,
which is a great way to segue into
automation and professional development.
Our grant was actually based on professional
development and professional development
instructors and offering it.
And through our discussions up here,
what we really talked about was the money it takes
for professional development is a whole 'nother
funding source to do that.
So our NSF pathways,
we did something called a Built program.
I dunno if you're familiar with that throughout the country.
Part of getting this program going is you have
to have a solid advisory.
I think everybody knows that, we don't need an advisory
committee that shows up for 10 minutes.
You have cookies, go home. It has to be as serious.
So this Built was part of NSF and people can do this.
It was live, This Built program, and I'll speak about it
'cause we're doing with industrial automation.
We did it with our additive was these were live,
these people were live, we had a hundred KSAs,
and they were live and they were voting on their phone.
So we did not invite instructors, only industry
specialists from NASA, from,
you name it, through the Bay area.
And they voted live on
what they thought we should be teaching.
And the unique thing was then I brought it to my instructors
and thought what they should be teaching.
And surprisingly, there was a difference,
surprisingly okay?
But nonetheless, we're gonna do
with all our programs coming up this same way.
And it's really neat.
It's a deal where they're voting one through four
and every KSA I could possibly come
up through this whole program.
So we'll build that.
I truly believe if you're gonna be successful,
you know, more than just talking
to your advisory once in a while
or going visit tours, they have to be connected, I mean,
forced connected to make that work.
So as far as some of the other stuff we're working on
a little bit, we have an IDRC grant,
which is gonna help us put equipment into the program.
We have other grants there,
advanced manufacturing partnerships that is a combination
of automation technicians and machinists.
So I think the goal, where I'm coming from
and what we're doing is how every one of our programs,
whether I can put automation into 3D printing,
which I think I can, automation into CNC machining
or the basic, if you don't have a technician
that could fix anything, then the rest of the areas are kind
of, kind of worthless there.
So that's kind of our approach to it
and where we wanna be funding wise
and what our plans are.
And obviously with NC3 and Festo starting us out,
we have an awesome foundation.
Sorry.
- So next we'll hear from Carol,
and there's a mic right there next to you.
- Hi, my name is Carol Reiley.
I'm known as the Mother of Robots.
For the past 20 years I've been working in AI
and robotics from, I think just doing lots
of different industries from Lansing and AIR Robotics.
I spent a long time in healthcare, you know, wanting
to bring a robot into every hospital.
I was at Intuitive Surgical, I was an instructor at Hopkins
and working at Intuitive to try to develop the pedagogy
of like, what does surgical training look like
and how do you standardize it globally?
And then, I had a shift where I was working on
what I could be more disruptive than healthcare,
which is self-driving cars.
So I had founded a company called Drive.ai
that was acquired by Apple in 2019.
And for the past five years have been working in the AI
and creativity space since I had believed that
that was an area that seem to be the core of humanity
and the thing that humans should try
to protect in the values.
So we work with the San Francisco Symphony
to curate tech programs.
So like how do humans and robots work together
and develop things that they couldn't independently?
So I think robots help people scale, to pick up boulders.
They can scale down to do microsurgery,
get rid of hand tremor reduction.
So how do you utilize and couple these two things
to make humans super creative, super strong, super anything.
So for the last five years, I've really been exploring
the arts space.
I work with the Exploratorium
to develop their new initiatives wing for AI.
I have an exhibit there right now.
And then I worked with the symphony and OpenAI
before it became OpenAI,
and have a Grammy nomination for an AI produced track.
So I think there's this interesting space as we're getting
so disruptive in both robotics and AI.
And if you go to the next slide, I think, you know, it's,
yeah, or even the one after that.
Yeah. So I just feel like now is the time.
I think there's been a shift.
It was like robotics in the 2010s that have been really,
and then there was a maker movement of 3D printing
and additive manufacturing, which had a wave.
And then deep learning really disrupted the AI field.
So it swung back to software.
And then I think now we're seeing the rise again
of robotics and automation.
So those are just my observations on that side. Thank you.
- Thanks Carol. And now we'll hear from Roger.
- Thank you Kevin.
I'm Roger Tadajewski, Executive Director
for the National Coalition of Certification Centers,
otherwise known as NC3.
And we were brought together by you all,
by community college presidents back in 2008, 2009,
came together to start to look at
how can education as a whole,
but just not at community colleges, but at high schools,
how do we really truly come together
if we're going to develop
and talk about industry recognized, industry developed
competency-based certifications, how do we do that?
And then how do we also work with the boards
of trustees, leadership all the way to the instructors,
so that we can drive and help that alignment with industry.
On the flip side of that is, if we could put that together,
our thought was back in 2008 to the how can we then work
with global leading industries
to help us develop those core competence,
those course certifications that are gonna be important
as they were then, as they are now to help drive
and build the infrastructure that we,
as we know we need always in the United States.
But most certainly as we continue to update,
whether it's our roads or technologies,
and we think about AI and energy and those pieces,
and how do we do all those things?
Well, you still need electricians and plumbers.
So as you look at the slide, every one of those companies
have over a hundred years of being up
in that upper fourth quadrant
of bringing new technologies into the global workspace.
So if you think about Lincoln Electric or Thermo King,
any of them, those are all corporations
that continue to lead in their areas.
So they are our key partners with us.
And then of course on, you know, if we just take Festo,
we were thinking about Festo
and you think about the food packaging, the biomedical
general manufacturing and those things,
probably in the United States in food and food packaging,
probably 80 or 85% of all food and food packaging
is probably done with Festo technology.
So think about everything under Coke or Pepsi
or Nestle's or all those that that is,
and that whole supply chain is being utilized in there.
And that continues to evolve.
So we work with them to bring those certifications
to light and then be able to deliver them
through great schools.
Like you'll hear from Hartnell and Foothills
that we are developing that
that can be delivered directly to the schools.
I won't go a whole lot in detail into it,
but just to give our audience some idea of,
when I talk about industry certifications,
these are the design and architecture
to each one of them are designed
so you can embed them into your for-credit program,
you can put 'em into a non-credit program,
you can put 'em into adult ed, apprenticeships,
dual enrollment, all those pieces that
that structure is already there and is operating.
So fast forward to 2025,
we have a little over 200 plus certifications
that are in our portfolio.
Again, all developed by industry.
And then those certifications then are also
underwritten by industry,
so they can be delivered without cost to your student.
So as you invest in your technology,
your professional development, those certifications
that you issue to your students,
there is not an additional cost there,
because the big picture goal is how do we help every student
in our communities be part of that social economic fabric?
And that's one of the things
that every one of these corporations are part of.
Next slide.
Just to give you a little bit of breadth and scope,
we operate in all 50 states,
a little over 600 plus community colleges.
We're right at almost 2000 K through 12 schools
that are operating as well as universities in Canada,
Jamaica, Puerto Rico and so forth that we're doing that.
So part of what I do want to touch on is is
great we hear about AI, right?
We're building all these things,
but what does that mean to you?
Do we have any college presidents in the room with us today?
Facilities, strategists, those kind of things.
Well, we're thinking about upgrades to our programs.
Yes, you can go update just like Mike is doing here,
but what we also gotta make sure is
that we include our facilities people
and our industry people.
Because the electricity that's coming into our colleges
and into our buildings that might have been built
in the sixties and seventies with one purpose
and an idea back then for 20 or 30 years.
There's a lot of infrastructure pieces that you need
to also be planning for today, but also in the future.
So, and it's not always about new buildings.
We can take and we work across the country,
we probably helped 400 plus colleges upgrade,
whether it's their HVAC programs, their refrigeration,
their welding programs.
So for example, this one here at Wichita is a building
that was built probably in the sixties,
but now it is a full fledged building automation system
controls lab, a learning lab where students not only
are learning the technology, but as the building changes
temperature, again, it's Wichita.
So there's days that it's a 108 degrees there.
How does that impact the environment and the classroom?
So students are getting real world activities every day
in there as they're going
through these certifications.
Next slide.
So this is Patrick and Henry in Virginia,
just outside of Dansville, this building here,
if you would go back about 10 years, 2010, 2011,
it was actually a NASCAR race car engine facility,
where they were building race car engines in,
and there was some combining of race car teams.
This building became available.
It did not look like this internally when they got it.
But like I say, we worked with a general contractor,
they did a lot of power washing,
cleaned it all up, and here's a great building
that had great bones, all that to it.
And now is one of our most advanced level three
robotics human machine interaction labs in the country.
So they are working directly.
And again, you know, as Carol touched on robotics
and healthcare, we think about our hospitals,
the infrastructure, the HVAC, the plumbing, the water,
whether it's data centers, hospitals,
our housing updates, all those things,
this core infrastructure right now in the United States has,
you know, close to 2 million jobs that
whether you're a contractor for buildings,
upgrading facilities, infrastructure of our roads
and bridges, all those things that are being built
are gonna be tremendous.
But the key thing that training all that will come
through you through the community colleges.
That is the only place
that it is being delivered can be delivered
and will be delivered in the future.
So we are working tirelessly across the country.
And then again with dual enrollment,
we are doing some projects even with middle school math
and science teachers to introduce them to the basic
of robotics and what are those key competencies that math,
hydraulics, physics that apply to that.
So students get engaged, their parents get engaged,
community can help drive that piece.
So I think that's the last slide, right? Yeah. Okay.
- Alright. Last but not least, let's hear from Richard.
- Yeah, hello Richard Chapman.
I teach agricultural engineering
and advanced manufacturing at Hartnell College in Salinas
in Monterey County.
And as far as I know, we are the first
and still only agricultural mechatronics associates
degree in the state.
And so what I'm doing is, well,
when they hired me a few years ago, five years ago now,
we did what's called a Dacom.
We got representatives from all
of our major agricultural companies in our community,
the top employers and said,
if you could design your perfect technician,
what are the skills and abilities and tools
and just everything they need to know
and do to perform their job.
And then we worked our way backwards into, you know,
getting some objectives and outcomes for the program.
And then I went to work on developing courses
and updating my degree in the program.
And that connected us with NC3 through
the equipment distributor.
And you know, there was other distributors that did bids
to outfit our shop with equipment.
We talk about shop upgrades.
If you were to walk into my, my shop when I was hired,
it was like a sheet metal shop.
Like they were sheet metal and cutting sheet metal
and like there's not a lot of jobs in agriculture,
where you're, you know, maybe for making gutters
or something, but that's not ag, you know,
so it was very interesting.
It was very 1980s. And so we did a big upgrade.
And the beauty about partnering with NC3
and their partner Festo is like Roger said,
most automation equipment and processing
and some of the outdoor automation is made by Festo.
And so when you use the Festo training equipment,
they're hands-on with the exact same parts
that they're gonna be hands-on in the real world,
which is really cool.
You know, you get other training equipment,
that's not necessarily the case.
It's a reduced version for education,
not necessarily the real part numbers that match,
same catalog, same everything.
So that was a huge benefit,
but took the information from that Dacom,
created a new sequence of courses.
This is my first community college job as well.
So learning the new world of community college
and the requirements there, you know, really trying
to meet the community's needs, you know,
'cause they have a lot of needs.
But to get that down into a two year degree
with general education requirements
and all that kind of stuff.
So, and then another unique situation that we deal
with in Salinas, you know, the type of crops
that we grow are very labor intensive.
So any company's trying to improve efficiency, well,
labor being a potential issue there,
especially when they can't fill all the jobs.
There's more jobs and they have people.
And then the food safety side of this as well.
Food safety is extremely important in
what we call specialty crops here
veggies and leafy greens,
'cause there's usually not what we call a kill step.
You know, those are things that are not cooked.
If you're making a salad, there's nothing,
you know, killing pathogens and stuff like that.
It's not cooked.
So you mentioned the clean room and medical stuff.
Well, agriculture and post harvest processing has its
own clean room type thing
and good agricultural practices that we have to follow.
And then to make things even more fun
during the winter months, they uninstall and pack up
and ship all this processing equipment
to Southern California and Arizona
'cause the growing season goes down there.
So that just makes things even more interesting, you know,
as far as reinstalling and recalibrating and plumbing
and electrical and anchoring
and all that kind of stuff.
All that equipment twice a year.
So I was able to take all that feedback
and create a sequence of classes.
And then considering the migrant workers that are part
of this, you know, they would really struggle
with a 16 week class.
So I took my 16 week classes
and my first two levels broke 'em down into two
eight week classes, two units each kind of a thing.
And so that way when the one class ends in the middle
of October and they're starting to transition to Yuma,
Arizona, they don't fail a 16 week class.
They actually pass the first class.
When they come back, they have the opportunity in March
to take the second level class.
So they're not just dead in the water.
They actually have the opportunity to continue
through their education and upskill.
And those classes, each being 72 hours also make it
really well for dual enrollment in high schools,
you know, one period and one semester,
72 hours is just about right as opposed
to a full 144 hour class in one semester.
They couldn't do that without multiple periods, which a lot
of high schools don't have the flexibility
to do two period blocks with their classes.
So that's pretty much where we're at.
Again, right now, really focus on the post harvest
value added technology.
So think bag salad, the automation technology
that goes into a bag salad or a veggie tray
or some of that value added stuff.
But really starting to explore now into the outdoor
automation principles of smart manufacturing and farming.
Starting a small partnership with John Deere
where they talked about digital twin
in their fields and stuff.
So pretty cool mapping your fields and stuff
and using principles, smart manufacturing,
automated harvesting, automated thinning
and weeding machines, that kind of stuff.
So single person department right now.
So it's a lot on my plate,
but definitely looking to expand as well.
- Fantastic, so you can see we have quite a variety
of backgrounds represented here.
And when we come to our questions, we wanted to start with,
and some of this has been covered a little bit by our panel,
but I want to put it out there.
So where are we now with respect to robotics, automation,
the impact of AI on those?
Give us an idea of basically how you see the industry
and then later on we'll get to where it's headed.
So maybe let's, since we finished with you,
Richard, let's start with you this time.
- Yeah so where we are currently in agriculture,
I mentioned about the labor challenges right now
in the tasks like thinning and harvesting.
So where we see the companies going right now is investing
and researching into automation technology
in the growing practices.
You know, the post-harvest technology,
like the bag salad type stuff
that's been automated since inception essentially.
And they're adding more automation palletization
with robots and stuff like that.
They're finding more ways to automate
and improve efficiency,
but that's not unlike any other manufacturing process
that's automated, you know,
but in the outdoor technology right now, you know,
so the labor intensive jobs like thinning weeds and stuff,
they've invented machines that use cameras
and AI technology to determine
where the crops are in the field and where the non crops
or the weeds would be in the field.
And maybe they're doing precision spraying with pesticide
or precision application or fertilizer to the crop.
So they're cutting their chemical inputs down by
like 80, 90, that alone.
Another option is like carbon robotics
and their laser weeding technology again, cameras, AI,
you know, machine learning to
where they're finding the crops or finding the weeds,
aiming and shooting lasers at the weeds.
Literally it's like Star Wars out in the fields right now.
And it's actually pretty cool because, you know,
you think 10 years ago if a student wanted
to become a mechanic in agriculture
and they wanted to work on machinery,
they need to learn lasers and like, you know,
they're generating a lot of electricity
on that mobile piece of equipment.
And then the AI and camera and that kind of technology.
So the skills gap is, you know, gigantic, right?
And then we're getting into
the harvesting technology as well.
And it's different games.
You know, if you have leafy greens, they're low
to the ground crop and the way they harvest
them is pretty low to the ground.
But then we also grow a lot of berries in my community,
strawberries being our number one commodity in my county.
And that's very easy to damage the strawberry if you try
to harvest that, you know, automated.
So they're trying to come up with new technologies,
you know, Festo's working on different gripper technology
for robots and stuff like that
that would be used in strawberries.
So, and then we have, you know, all the greenhouse practices
as well becoming more automated vertical farming,
getting into automated transplanting, you know,
with a company Plant Tape
that does automated transplanting and stuff.
So that's, again, we're improving efficiencies anywhere
any other manufacturing company would.
It's just in the agriculture world.
- So let's shift from agriculture to the creative space,
Carol and some of the other industries you've worked
in since it's such a broad spectrum.
- Sure so, you know, I think we often say like,
AI is the new electricity
since it pervades every single industry.
You know, I think it will be quite disruptive
to the workforce and how we think about the future of work
in many different ways.
I'm starting to try to figure out how do you,
I feel like it's extremely hard
for like college graduates nowadays to find entry level jobs
and everyone is upskilling.
So you essentially need the skills of like a CEO
to be able to manage and tell AI what to do.
And once again, it's like having a thousand bad interns
that you have to keep checking their work
and like make sure what you said is
actually executed correctly.
So I think that that like critical thinking skill is
necessary and like very democratized
in the sense that like, I'm seeing like fifth graders
come up with projects that took grad students, you know,
like years to uncover.
So it's a weird shift in how quickly people can learn
and how asynchronous everything is.
But I think that I'm like, I'm extremely hopeful
for like new types of things coming out.
It's just gonna be happening so quickly.
So just trying to, I mean, I think it's a full-time job just
to like read the news about what is happening in robotics
and in automation at this point.
So, and I think I'm really interested
in the upskilling of people
and then also how to preserve like different values
and how do people interact together.
Like my work is in, you know, human computer interactions,
so how do we and robots coexist together
and how do we utilize each other's strengths?
And on the flip side, just human to human interaction
I think has the, is gonna be redefined.
So really looking at
how people interact with these machines.
So you don't always just have like ChatGPT answers.
And I think we're looking at like in the music industry,
authentication, artist rights, new types of performances.
So like things like ballerinas and robots dancing together
and new art forms.
You know, I think there's a lot of opportunity
for us to look for new ways
and like remove ourselves from the drudgery of tedious tasks
that you may not want to do.
But then I'm really trying to think about like
that core group of high school to college level kids
and how to upskill them quick enough in this new world,
so that they still find interesting jobs
or if it moves to like more of a gig economy.
So just open questions on that side at this point
as we go into exploration.
- So I think that is a good kind of juxtaposition
between a pretty focused field
and the state of kind of where we are
with respect to agriculture.
I like the way Carol, you framed the ideas related to
how the span of ages is changing,
how ready people are for taking on robotics
and automated industry type tasks
and actively being the architects of the solutions.
Maybe Roger, you can tell us a little bit about the current
state of certifications
and preparing people as we heard needs
to happen at a faster rate now.
And there's a mic in front of you as well.
- This one's not working.
- Alright, there you go.
- Yeah, just to build on what Richard
and Carol touched on from an education
and certification standpoint, you know,
just if we think about for our instructors,
whether it's at the high school
or community college level, you know, let's just kind
of think about, right one piece I'd add to that builds
onto Richard touched on food
and creating those salad bags and all that.
Well that gets put into a trailer that's refrigerated.
And a big big part of that is called Thermo King.
And but that could be pharmaceuticals, could be a lot
of things that it could leave California
and be expected be in Chicago
by less than 12 hours.
So historically that refrigerated unit
and that could be put on a railroad car.
You see the railroad cars,
next time you see railroad cars going by
and you have 80 of 'em, you gotta wait, just look at
how many of 'em actually have a refrigerated unit
on that rail car that's going by.
They're running, they've got refrigeration going,
they've got a auxiliary power unit,
typically a little small diesel engine in there running.
And historically they just ran
and they hoped by the time it got to its destination
and everything was good, right?
It was supposed to be a 38 degrees,
leaves California, gets to Chicago,
hopefully it's at 38 degrees.
Now, there was a lot of loss in food and food product
and other high value product up to about 2011, 2012.
Already today those units are already
connected to the cloud.
The AI is part of that infrastructure already.
So now today when that rail car
or that truck leaves California
and is going somewhere, it is literally being tracked
and followed every second all the way.
And if they see it go, it's supposed to be at 38 degrees
and it drops down to 37 in the middle of Kansas,
well it might be just ambient temperature that's adjusting
and they'll pay attention to it.
But if it goes up to 44 degrees,
they're gonna be pulling that rail car off.
They've already used AI to look at the data
to see what's happening on it.
They will pull that rail car off in St. Louis
or wherever it be, they'll have a technician on that
working on that, protect that material and get that going.
So to teach all that, all those certifications,
that's again, as I mentioned earlier, comes through you all,
through the community colleges.
So one of the things that NC3 is,
and Richard can touch on this
and Mike will be going through this very soon,
is our professional development.
Our goal is how do we help your instructors
learn this technology, go through it,
and how do we help you come up to 80, 85%
of what current technology is?
We connect you directly to the industry,
global industry partner on that.
And then we sustain that by update training,
constant contact communications on that,
and then doing professional development.
And I could go on and on, but if we think about welding
and you touched on the medical industry.
So welders today that are welding in that product
that's going into the hospital medical industry,
there's basically a birth certificate for every piece
of equipment that's going in there.
It's being who welded it, what it was put together.
All that is already utilizing AI
in that engineering tracking process.
So the welders today coming out of you,
if you have a welding program,
welders today in the industry already are utilizing AI
in their preparation, their planning, their layouts,
the equipment that they're using is attached.
All those things are all been becoming normalized.
And it's a great thing.
But the important part is
for you at these institutions,
it's a huge opportunity
because students come through your programs
and get those skill sets.
The companies that also want to upskill their workers
or higher in other people, they, you know, just
as Richard touched, there's a lot of short term training
that is coming back that generates revenue.
Four year programs, I was just in DC
and I visited with a gentleman
from Green County Career Center in Ohio
that said he had something like 150 current employees,
incumbent workers that came
during the summer back to his program to go
through some welding certifications, some QA,
some precision measurement certifications
and that drove that revenue but also got those businesses
and industries better connected to the school
in that pipeline piece.
So those are things that we're doing now already
across the country and communities
and quite frankly, we're doing quite a bit already
in California, but we've got a lot more work to do.
And I'll touch on that in a little bit on
where we want to continue to grow.
- I'm just gonna touch in a little bit on
where the AI comes into our program
and already has a little bit with the future.
I think what you've seen is agriculture.
So you've seen hundreds of acres, we've seen welding,
hundreds of cars.
it's large quantities.
I think the key to the Bay area
to be successful is we have close to two,
I send out 200 to 300 cards every quarter
to smaller businesses that have 10 to 40 employees.
How do you get them to use automation?
It is very successful.
So there's a big company that's working
with a smaller company
but with the object with smaller companies.
What we're trying to work with them is they're not making
thousands, they're making 20, 30, 40.
So anytime you're working anything in automation
and you need to change speeds, a human has to change
grippers or grippers have to change.
All these things have to change that require a person
where the automation we're trying to work on
with a company is pick and place type stuff for,
and they're subcontractors
for the lambs, for everybody else.
What we're working on with the company
and trying to do with the college is the machine
can actually, as you go home, we could run that part
of 20, 10, 15, 30,
and this machine's capable of changing the grippers,
doing all the work through AI commands overnight
to do a series of parts, 10 at a time, 20 at a time
'cause I'll admit being a small business owner
for many years, I wouldn't have thought of automation
to make 10 parts or 20 parts or whatever.
But take that one more step.
I have a student that bought two machines, has automation in
between these machines, runs it by himself
and runs 40 different parts on a weekend.
And this thing's smart enough
to pick up the different shapes
and do stuff while he's not there.
So our goal in automation is not so much the hundreds,
thousands, millions, it's that we would like
to get it to all of the small communities
and the big communities, don't get me wrong, we've worked
with Tesla, we've worked with other ones,
but I think you'd be amazed if you focused in on
how many small businesses support the big ones that need
to be automated too, because of a skills gap.
And that's our big problem is the skills gap.
- Thanks Mike.
So we wanted to talk a little bit about the workforce itself
and how we can create a more diverse workforce in our
role here in the California community colleges 2.1 million
students and it's one of the most diverse educational
environments in the country, right?
And so as we are looking at opportunities
to get into robotics and automation,
how do we create entryways?
Again, it may be at the fifth grade level
as Carol suggested earlier,
but even within our own student body, when a student says,
"I don't quite know what I wanna major in,
or I don't quite know what I want to do,"
like how do we reach those students
and how do we make sure that we're making opportunities
available to all the communities, even those
that might be not normally represented.
So I'm gonna start maybe with you again, Mike,
and we'll work our way back the other way.
- Sure.
The obvious one is, as you mentioned,
is working with the high schools and dual enrollment.
We're fortunate enough where the dual enrollment comes
to our college to work with our equipment.
It's quite obvious in the Bay area
that no high school has the amount of equipment
that we have at the community college to work with.
That's a big one.
Our NSFATE grant that I talked about
focused directly on this problem right here.
It's not a surprise that in some of these industries
needs a lot more female employees
that that's a surprise.
So we worked with veterans,
different individuals was the focus of our grant
of bringing underrepresented individuals
in through various stations.
Mark sitting over here, we're doing a program now where
through the Department of Rehabilitation that,
it's called UAA, I'm working for 12 weeks with,
you talk about underrepresented programs with
high functioning adults with autism,
trying to work in a program.
Now they're graduating to get them to have them jobs.
Now the unique thing is other part of the countries
with this same program,
there's an automation program coming up in part
of the program to get these same individuals in.
So we're representing everybody,
but quite obviously our goal at DeAnza is, you know,
bringing the various diversified,
underrepresented populations into these great paying jobs
that they can be successful, obtain a degree,
and if they'd like, we have a plan
for a four year degree too.
So we kind of have something for everybody.
- Yep, I touched on this
and this is super important, you know, the diversity
and how do we really, you know,
move from just a PowerPoint slide
and really put it in action.
So some of the things that NC3 is doing is,
I'll start with this we work with schools to how do we help
a community college or a high school program
become a destination, a choice,
that where the students want to be there, they would look at
that welding program, mechatronics program, ag program,
plumbing program, electricity program, whatever it is,
and they go, "Wow, I want to be part of that."
Now the harsh reality is,
is I will tell you I spend probably 20%
of my time in any given month
walking into whether it's a college program
or high school programs,
and sometimes I say, wow,
really you haven't done anything in this program in the last
40 years as it looks like that.
Sometimes I walk in the programs
and I use the slogan, I've gotta have a flashlight
to see what's going on while the lights are
still on in the place.
Okay so that starts with leadership.
We just have to be honest in our communities
because when we walk in or industry walks in
and they go, "Wow, you are all 20 or 30 years behind,"
they're gonna nod their head,
they'll come to the advisory committee meeting,
but they're gonna leave and they're gonna try
and figure out a different pathway.
And you see it in the newspapers, you see it
where companies are saying,
well, we're gonna start our own training programs.
There's a reason behind that.
And what we've gotta all do is,
is make sure if we're gonna help students
and create a destiny choice,
especially the single parent student,
the student that's living with a grandparent or an aunt
or an uncle and they don't know even how to get to you.
And when they do get there, they go,
"Boy, this is not what I'm looking at."
And they're not, it doesn't look like technology
and it's maybe not even clean.
And so we're working on those things along with,
at the same time, we spend some time on a thing
we call National Signing Day
that when students come to Hartnell from a high school
on a trip and come and see what's happening there
and we create those environments
to where they come back just like collegiate, you know,
I live in Oklahoma actually,
and you know, we steal some football players
from Texas and Kansas, right?
And you have these big signing days.
Well, why don't we recognize students that are choosing
to go into healthcare
or going into plumbing, these other areas.
So we do that to create that.
and for young women, minorities,
people that don't think that they've ever gonna
have a chance, we do a lot of those areas as well
and engage the parents
and bring our industry partners in there, help drive that.
But also spending time with that math and science teachers
and counselors to help them know.
And because this is also part of the employability skills,
so that when we help young people come in
and they go, "Wow, I want to be there,"
well then that automatically gets them
going to show up on time.
They wanna be part of that.
They are engaged and the instructor
and the institutions become a place of inspiration
that all ends up in industry, industry gets engaged
and it becomes contagious in a good way.
And that's what is a big part of helping us grow
and drive what we do at NC3,
since our inception back in 2010.
- They're passing off.
I want to add one thing.
I really forgot the most important part
is having a diverse faculty okay.
I have instructors that can teach three languages, Spanish,
Vietnamese, and we in our manufacturing program, which is,
you know, machining everything,
we brought a female instructor in.
So I think it's key that the instructional part
of your program also represents a diverse area.
And that will bring in, it'll give it,
we need a more inclusive program through feeling people
and what we're delivering and who's delivering it
and what we represent.
That's the one I forgot.
- Yeah, I mean I agree and I think it's a hard pipeline
problem, right?
'cause I think we're seeing like the faculty
or people who were educated 20 plus years ago.
So those are like things that we're catching up on.
And I do, I think there's a great book from like
the nineties "Unlocking the Clubhouse,"
which really talks about women
in the computer science field.
You know, there's a professor at MIT Media Lab,
Mitch Resnick, who teaches the lifelong
kindergarten lab in scratch.
He developed scratch programming.
But he says like, vote the projects that you need
to think about building for the curriculum is really like
low floors, high ceilings, wide walls, right?
So you really want people to be able to join at any level
and then be able to scale up as far as they can.
And then also have a wide variety of projects.
So like one of my most influential classes
was motor sensors and actuators.
And it was a, we had to build a robot that created art,
that had human input.
So you could scream into it
and it could spray paint, it could be whatever you wanted.
And you work with groups and you know,
I think there's something about non-competitive classes
because I think first robotics is great
for turning it into a sport
and that appeals to like,
it's completely changed like this young
generation of roboticists.
But the on the other hand, it like has a different branding
and it deters like certain type of person.
So like Julia Robinson Math Festival is fantastic
to get like people into math.
It's non-competitive, like 10 grams essentially problem
solving at Hopkins
because it's healthcare related.
You know, I think a lot of it's marketing, right?
So like the biomedical program
and computer science now has over 50% women
'cause I think, you know, it's this desire
to like wanna help or mission driven people.
I think it's not just women,
but just a certain type of person
who wants to be mission driven.
Berkeley changed their coding class name to the art
and beauty of coding and it became,
it instantly like popped up 20% you know?
So I feel like there's this,
the way you pose your curriculum
and the title affects the students who choose to enroll
and that has like a network effect.
I think it's great to have a diversity of faculty,
whether it be gender, racial, introverts versus extroverts.
It's just someone that students can connect with
that like, they feel included.
And I think there also needs to be an intellectual peer.
So someone, if someone's taking a class,
I think they're more willing to with a partner.
So I think those are just some of the things.
It doesn't have to be someone that looks like you,
but just that you need someone along.
- Yeah, I don't think I have a whole lot more to add
that's already been said.
I think a lot of the work for,
you know, for me to be able
to train a diverse workforce is starts in the high schools
or possibly middle school.
You know, we have some local high schools that
maybe have like an engineering pathway,
but the companies in our community, they might have like 10
to one technicians to engineers.
So if you're trying to look at the, you know,
filling the jobs, they're not gonna be filling a lot
of engineered jobs, but they will be filling
a lot of technician jobs.
So maybe the high schools need to take a better look.
And I don't wanna talk down on all the high schools
and stuff, but I, you know, I taught high school
for eight years, so I have an idea of what goes on there.
You know, I get a lot of students
that come in outta high school
and they just dislike math.
It's like, well the whole world runs on math,
especially in this field, right?
So, you know, maybe if they could find more creative ways
to teach math and physics to their students, that'd be cool.
I think actually the mechatronics training could even,
you know, find a way to replace their math in physics class.
You know, whatever work has to go in there,
but that's what I'm teaching 'em is
math and physics and everything.
So yeah, I mean, that's a great question.
You know, Hartnell does a lot of work.
We're a Hispanic serving institution,
and we get a lot of, you know, immigrant students that,
you know, are not strong in English language.
So finding ways to support those students,
obviously I'm sure everybody in here has been
working on that as well.
So, you know, that's no different for us.
But I would like
to see the high schools do a little different,
I think the awareness piece, you know,
if we get students that don't know
that mechatronics is a career path, so that's something
as well, you know, they know welding
and automotive are career paths, but, or nursing,
but maybe they're not aware of their emerging technology
and manufacturing and agriculture.
So I don't wanna, you know,
pass the buck to the high schools.
But I would like to see the high schools
do a little better job at this.
- Thanks Richard and I would say you do have a lot to add,
so keep adding.
And I would even recall something that you said earlier
that fits within this context.
You changed the unit value
and nature of your course to fit the lifestyles
and lived experiences of your students
and that creates opportunities for people
who otherwise would be excluded.
So I just wanna recognize that you rock.
- Thank you, if I could use that, that's a good point.
I appreciate that; not that I rock,
but what you said about the classes
and something that I'm really interesting is our county
is pretty spread out,
and we attract students from, you know, Santa Clara County
and San Bernardino County as well and all in Santa Cruz.
So, you know, we reach pretty far
and it's a long drive.
It's a dangerous drive.
And you know, finding ways to find, you know,
to try to do some distance ed,
it's hard 'cause these are hands-on skills, you know,
but that could be another emerging technology in education.
- Well, and so an idea from another panel,
you may have all seen in the exhibition space a giant booth
called Dreamscape Learn.
So they have these pods, but Cerro Coso Community College
and the current community college district has, I don't know
how many acres of space,
and it's a long drive for anybody to get anywhere.
So they are getting one of those pods mounted on a trailer,
and they're gonna drive it around to make it more accessible
for the students to participate
and learn these biology skills without having to drive two,
three hours to get to a campus.
And so, you know, that may be an idea as well.
We have about 10 minutes left, so I would love
to do this last one as a lightning round
and then we'll open it up to questions from the audience.
And it's really, and some of you have been hinting
at this all along, but we've talked about the present
and how to diversify the workforce.
We can't talk at a futures summit without talking
about the future, right?
So I'm gonna literally say maybe one minute each
and then we'll ask the crowd
what questions they have for us.
They've had an hour to think
and all the cookie sugar to get their brains running.
- You know, just quickly that I could say is AI
in my area, it's obviously gonna eliminate lower skilled
jobs, that's a given.
But what we're teaching these students now
is higher skilled jobs.
We're gonna upskill them, they're gonna make more money
where there's gonna be more opportunities.
But the AI in manufacturing is it's here,
it's actually been here already.
What we've been doing already, we've been doing forever.
We've been entering some data and equipment.
We've been making these things go by themselves for years,
whether it be CAM systems and other things.
I think the word AI's unique to us,
but actually we've been doing it already.
It's only gonna get better as far as the robots automation
type stuff and things of that.
So it is the future,
but I will say it's been here a lot in the past already too.
- Yeah, I would add, you know,
the fundamentals don't go away with AI.
So, you know, I just spent some time a couple weeks ago
with the folks with train, you know,
and they're using AI out on the field.
So, but the technician, the engineers understanding
and having a good understanding of airflow
and heat transfer, those fundamentals of measurement
and science, those don't change.
But what does change is AI can give you bad information.
And what really accelerates the problem then is,
is if the technician and the engineer
doesn't have a good understanding
of those fundamentals of what they mean.
And so when they get the wrong technical service from the AI
or a direction, they can get themselves in trouble.
In some cases it's, you know,
high electrical voltage areas that,
it can be a problem.
So from our colleges, our fundamentals, Richard just,
it's not about trigonometry and calculus,
it's the fundamentals of math and geometry that are going
to be even more important from understanding
AI will help you get those things,
but you also gotta know the reality of
what these pieces are.
So, those things are here already.
The other part of this then is how do we continue
to work with our colleges across the country,
and a network of pieces and Kevin touched on this,
we're spending time with middle school math teachers
and science teachers to help them be inspirational
about AI but also the fundamentals that they're teaching,
so that we can help those students.
And one thing I'll just do a little pre for,
for Richard as he passed the mic down,
we're gonna be doing some a first
of its kind professional development right here
in California.
And I'll let Richard do the invitation to that,
but we look forward to engaging and doing more.
- So I think that first principles
and actually the four Cs is probably gonna be critical
to like really figure out how to sort through the BS
as well as real time interactions with people, right?
Because I think right now facts are widely accessible.
So what's gonna be most important is real time
face to face interactions as you're going AI against AI
'cause you guys can all interact, so can you guys be able
to work on the skills of like influencing,
be able to calmly debate?
I think that that will be very important moving
forward here as we'll be able to access facts very easily,
and then if you have time to respond through email,
you can very easily cater.
But I do think that it's being able to correctly prompt,
be able to think through if the answer actually makes sense.
And then I think this like really soft skill of like
that real time interactions between people.
- Yeah just real quick on what's in the future,
we talked about improving efficiency in the labor intensive
tasks and agriculture,
but I guess on the AI side, specifically
using what's called SCADA Supervisory Control
and Data Acquisition for the manufacturing process.
The machines, condition monitoring
of machines leading into prescriptive maintenance
and predictive maintenance on machines.
So that's, you know, a technician's day would be,
you know, their schedule would be shaped
by AI based on what these sensors are feeding back
on the conditions of the machines.
You know, if we break down in the production run
that's leafy greens with the expiration date,
the clock is ticking, you know, so, you know,
having a really good maintenance schedule using AI
for that as well.
- Fantastic. Thank you.
- Oh, you want me to talk about that too? The training?
Yeah, so thank you Roger for that. Yeah.
At the end of this month, the first ever
NC3 train the trainer will be at Hartnell College
in Salinas, September 29th or 30th through October 3rd.
That week it's four days
and I'll be training instructors on introduction
to mechatronics and fundamentals of electricity,
kind of our foundational skills that we need
and smart manufacturing and mechatronics.
So, you know, it's part of a grant to really, you know,
improve our dual enrollment pipeline,
but it's really just to kinda get more training out there.
So if you have any instructors that are interested
by completing the train the trainer, they're allowed
to now certify their students on the topics given
that they have the equipment
and they've completed the train the trainer,
and yeah, that's pretty much that yeah.
- So have you got any hand raisers? Come and see us.
I think you have all five
or six seats open that we can, happy to add anybody from
the community or California to come and be part of that.
- Sounds good.
We'll make sure that the information is passed along
to the organizers of this event,
so that we can have a QR code
for people to sign up.
We do have about three to five minutes left, depending on
how much you stick to Pacific Standard Time.
So we have time for at least one question.
So how many of you have been thinking all along
"I really wanna hear an answer to this."
Got someone in the back and then we'll sneak you in.
I believe we have a half hour break
before the next event, so if folks wanna stick around.
I don't know if the panelists have time.
- [Livia] Yes, thank you so very much.
My name's Livia and I teach engineering
and AI in Folsom Lake College,
and I wanted to help more students like at least like,
get jobs after they learn AutoCAD and Fusion.
And these are like tools also for automation.
So I'm wondering like with robotics
and with automation and emerging technology,
do you consider this as a disruption in technology?
It's exponentially changing and it's rapidly like evolving.
So did the KRA change over automation
after applying robotics?
Because I'm wondering if we're kind of like eliminating
skills and jobs for blue collar jobs
and like most of the graduate of the community colleges,
the value in the culture change afterwards
with automation, this field and technology.
How long does the certification last?
Because I know like sometimes it's like two years,
but I just wanted to clarify like
so I can like get my student engaged,
take this certification's gonna be good for your future
or something like that.
And yeah, and hoping that there can be more internship
and apprenticeship program in between community colleges
and the industry sector.
And that's all. Thank you.
- Really quick, part of the question was on Fusion and CAD,
whether that be of value or not.
Was that part of the question?
- [Livia] Yes. Of value or not?
- So I'm gonna say another part
of our program is a CAD degree, whatever, CAD Fusion,
NX Creo, those are never gonna go anywhere.
AI and the equipment that runs it
will never even be developed
unless you can draw, you can create,
you can engineer and you can make it.
So I would keep teaching that all the way.
I would never stop that.
That's just actually, in manufacturing mechanical,
that is the stepping stone to everything that we do.
So that's, I would stay that route for sure.
I don't remember the rest. Which one?
- Part of the question was on the certifications as well.
The NC3 certifications don't have an expiration date.
So if your student has certifications that, you know,
that's not like they have to recertify on something,
but it's not necessarily a license to operate something
or a license to perform a skill.
It's really gonna help in their interview process show.
I've been trained on specific equipment to do
specific tasks at a high level
industry standard on the manufacturer's equipment,
manufacturers have huge input into that.
Mentioned the blue collar jobs
and you know, some of that being replaced.
But again, somebody is still gonna have
to install these systems, calibrate these systems,
repair these systems.
I don't see that being fully automated
where there's zero human interaction.
It's really is a collaboration human and machine.
So luckily NC3 has certifications
in those skills as well.
Electrical wiring and plumbing skills in that as well.
- [Raheem] Hi, my name is Raheem.
I'm with AQL Labs,
but I'm also a trustee
for the Seattle colleges up in Washington state.
And the question I have is, so maybe it was answered
by your previous question,
but it's really about the pace of change
that's happening with AI
and the time it takes for colleges
to build certification programs, pathways, et cetera.
And so like, I guess one of the things
that I'm trying to figure out is as AI accelerates,
so rapidly and you made a statement about,
well, these medium skill
or higher skilled things that AI will not do.
I'm personally not so sure about that,
but I wanted to know more about
A, why you're so confident about that,
but B, how can colleges design pathways
they can't be future proof,
but you know, that are not getting made
retrograde in like a year or two year,
like, you know what I mean?
'cause I feel like the pace of AI
improving is very rapid,
and how can we develop skilling programs that outpace
that in a way.
- I think you were referring to the AI
and the skills.
Correct.
- Yeah what I would say to that
from my perspective is working
with all the global companies I work with is that,
is there higher skilled stuff
that AI will have an impact on?
Yes, but the ability to take
and completely replace an engineer
that's gonna be designing a train
20 ton HVA system controller and cooler,
it's still gonna be built
all that engineering in there, all those pieces,
the materials, the makeup, all that stuff
that's gonna come together from a manufacturing process
standpoint, that's not going away.
Or if we think about aviation,
Airbus and Boeing are both have composite planes now.
Five years ago, finishing that composite on that plane
was a lot of hand operation.
Today, 3M and its abrasive division
has a robot that handles all that
rudimentary work that you, actually,
but the person that the people that used to do that
are now moved up into the process actually at a higher
level to manage all that.
And actually both the workers doing less manual labor
and tends the opportunity to make mistakes where the robot
has really refined that whole finishing process.
Save time and productivity and those kind of things.
So those are just a couple examples.
Same thing in ag, those pieces.
So, but you know, things still break down.
Things still need maintenance, things still wear out.
And as new technologies
and new robotic pieces come into play,
well then someone's gotta integrate that.
Someone's gotta commission it.
And all those other pieces,
there's a lot of similarities to 1910 through 1920
when we started to electrify pieces of equipment.
And so yes, there used to be, if you go back
and read it, you know, in the early days of the automobile,
it used to take about 17 people
to paint a car because they were painted it by hand.
Well, DuPont and these other figured out how to spray it,
automation, all that.
And it went down to two people, well what happened
to the other 15?
They didn't get laid off.
They got into the production and these other pieces.
Will there be ebbs and flows in that curve
as we work through those things?
Absolutely but every one of those,
and I appreciate you as a trustee being here
because it's really at your level that, boy,
we need more trustees in these things
because that pace of change and adaptation
that's happening in our communities,
it's one of the things I work on,
how do we help trustees stay up with this?
Well you're still running your own business
and doing these other things
'cause it impacts that community, right?
And impacts our instructors and that leadership.
So, those are some things that, boy,
from that strategic thing that we used
to have five years to figure out.
Now sometimes we might be lucky if we have 18 months
to figure it out at a trustees level
and that what are those things?
So, there's a lot of pieces in there,
but I can't overemphasize
what I hear from the global leaders.
These fundamentals, these key things don't go away.
They actually are amplified to a higher level
of understanding that you need to have going forward.
- Yeah, I think it's a great question
and I think I'm just gonna add to it that,
just to go back historically, you know,
I had referenced the AI as the new electricity.
When electricity came out there were chief electricity
officers where people had to decide if they were AC or DC
you know, and then now it just becomes running
in the background and it just works.
And I think the same thing will happen to AI,
but right now we're in a shock.
Same thing with cars.
When they came out, like people were so freaked out
that they had to paint
and cut out basically wooden cutouts
and put 'em in front of cars to give the illusion that like,
you know, a horse is smart enough to stop
before then the cliff, if you weren't paying
attention, you might drive off a cliff.
I think it's almost human society accepting it.
Now AI is very disruptive
and you know, I think now they're,
it's happening so fast.
I think for the colleges and instructors,
it's really hard on you since you have
to like learn fast and keep ahead of the students.
So I think it's great that there's MOOCs available.
So if you wanna do some quick training,
you can stay ahead of it.
I think we're gonna also, it would be beneficial
to have more student led projects
so that their portfolios can build,
and if you can direct them towards blue ocean type projects,
like I think ag is a great example where lots of problems
and like migrant workers, you know, like I feel like it's
very like California specific too.
So, I feel like direct them towards new problems
that aren't the everyday so they can find new solutions
and create something different,
because I think there's so much opportunity in different
industries that are not where your first instincts are.
- [Host] Fantastic. Well, would you all please join me-
- We got one more.
- [Host] Do you all have time for one more? Okay.
- [Participant] Hopefully this is a quick question.
I could be quick, wondering that dual enrollment
and concurrent enrollment, if that makes sense
in your areas, has there been an increase?
Has that improved over the last several years?
If not, what have been the barriers?
- Well, I can tell you from a national level,
it's certainly improved.
So I can tell you know, in say Kenosha, Wisconsin,
where Gateway Technical College there has,
like they went from 2000 students being in dual enrollment
up to 7,000 students being in dual enrollment.
Same thing in Wichita and North Carolina.
There's a lot of that that now is it,
does it just happen overnight? No.
Is there sometimes resistance
of high schools, Richard, you touched on it a little bit.
They go, "Nope, here's our lane
and community colleges, that's your lane."
And so sometimes we've gotta help see that just like
technology that this is a good thing,
but it's gotta be worked through
and you gotta get it going.
So, but I think it's an awesome thing.
- Really quick, I can just basically speak
for DeAnza College, what we do,
it's increased every quarter.
We went from, we had to do combination classes,
but it's is manufacturing now, this is not history,
you know, like other kind of stuff.
But in the manufacturing area it has grown every quarter.
A little more fine tuning we're doing,
we're really close to doing classes by themselves
without having to backfill with other people.
But it has grown every quarter to where we've added a class.
So you can go from two to four to six,
and we're only going with a couple of
high schools now we have it.
But as far as the manufacturing now,
and the only reason I'll say this in the Bay area is
because I went to high school down the street, the same one
we service had equipment.
There is nothing there now.
The only thing there, which was great,
we talk about the First Robotics.
The First Robotics is great,
but it doesn't encompass all the students.
I'm gonna be straightforward.
It's a series of students, but for the hands-on ones,
I think automation will be good.
Machining 3D printing the whole bit it is increasing.
I'm anticipating adding more and filling them stuff.
So it's going one way and it is by 50% or more
has increased the enrollment of females by far, by far.
- Yeah so for me, you know,
our dual enrollment sections have definitely increased.
Probably like a state initiative, you know, leading that
obviously, probably we're all feeling similar parts there.
But some of the barriers in my community in my area,
the state K-12 ag mechanics standards,
agriculture mechanic standards don't,
they've not been updated in over a decade.
And so there's, I'm part
of the California Agriculture Teachers Association,
and we have our meetings and we collaborate on that.
But, so now there's talks,
but definitely, you know,
if the high school instructors not seeing standards
be updated and they're so focused on standards,
that kind of is a little bit of a hangup.
Another one is the university programs are not necessarily
training teachers on modern skills necessarily.
I guess I can just talk about ag mechanics class
and the lab teaching methods classes
at some of the universities are teaching.
It's no different than it was in like the seventies,
eighties, you know, early nineties kind of a thing.
So that needs to be updated,
but you know, I don't know how they measure that to be able
to adjust those classes
'cause the universities are successful in general.
So that's interesting how they would adjust that.
So the need for professional development, you know,
we have a very, a lot of passionate teachers,
agriculture teachers, especially in our community,
but they need to be exposed
to the technology and the skills.
So professional development training for them.
Another barrier I'm seeing is high school administrators,
for whatever reason, some school districts are just,
and I understand you don't wanna just jump in
and make all these mistakes, you know,
but they're almost being too hesitant
or too cautious in adopting dual enrollment.
Another thing I wanna see is in high schools, you don't need
to put every single one
of your students on a university track.
You know, that's not realistic
and you're setting 'em up for failure when you do that.
You know, their second year is all remediation.
They're not gonna be,
they're not all gonna be university bound
right outta high school.
So I think every high school should have
a CTE pathway requirement.
The high school I taught at did have a CTE
pathway requirement.
We also had an eight period schedule,
which is huge as a split block.
So we were project based focused.
So your classes were an hour and a half long
and is very project focused.
So, you know, a lot of high schools
are still a six period schedule
and they put 'em university bound,
which means they have no opportunity
for CTE classes in their first two years of high school.
So I don't know, I don't mean to bash all the high schools.
I love the high schools, but yeah, they need
to be more forward thinking for sure.
- [Host] There we go, that brings us back to the future
and your future hopefully will be including
helping me thank the panel for all their great work.
(audience applauding)
And please come up and say hello, ask more questions,
but I know other folks are getting ready to move on
to the next event.
And so thank you all and enjoy the rest of the summit.
- You know, put your information.
- Yeah will do and we're all connected
through email from Kevin.